Open the eyelid that conceals the night
夜ヲ覆ウ目蓋開ケ
凶キ影ヲ恐レルナカレ
And fear not the evil shadows
I am as a doll
仄くらき柩から
Born from a dusky coffin
産み堕とされた人形のように
With a growing body frozen red
躰は赤く凍え
And a heart soothed by darkness
心は闇にあやされ育つ
Can you see me?
君に僕が見えるかい
My nails steeped in fresh blood
つなぐ手の冷たさに
Sink into the chill of our joined hands
鮮血の爪立てる
Now, let me see you frown
眉寄せてごらんよ
壊し合おう先に続く 謎に満ちる結末を
Let us destroy one another
And face the ending full of mystery that lies ahead
Before we rot away in emptiness
羽も脚ももがれたまま
With our wings and legs ripped away
虚空のなか朽ち果てるより
There is another me
もうひとり僕がいて
Who loves someone so much it hurts
誰かを痛いほど愛しているんだ
I wonder, which one is the illusion?
さぁどっちが幻だろうね
Everyone out!
皆出なさい
外へ
Call the police and an ambulance, now!
大至急 警察と救急を
Was anyone hurt?
怪我した者はいないな
Are you all right?
榊原くん 君は
I'm okay.
大丈夫 です
Let's go, Sakakibara.
行こう 榊原くん
It looks like making two students
not exist didn't work.
駄目だった みたいね 「いないもの」を二人に増やしても
I'm at my wit's end.
もう疲れた
疲れました
I'm so tired.
I don't know what to do.
どうしたらいいのか 分からないんです
Mr. Kubodera...
久保寺先生
I'm sure you understand.
あなたなら 分かってくれますよね
I leave the rest to you.
後は よろしくお願いします
That troubled me.
あれが気にかかって 仕方なかったんだ
Sorry.
すまんね
Anyway,
それでだ
the results of an investigation of
Mr. Kubodera's home
警察が先生の自宅を調べに行ったところ
were disturbing.
大変なことになっていたらしい
久保寺先生は独身で
Mr. Kubodera was a bachelor
ずっと母親と二人暮らしでね
who still lived with his mother.
She was well on in years,
母親はもう高齢で
and had been bedridden for some time,
due to a serious illness.
重病をお患って寝たきりの生活が長いこと続いていたらしんだが
They found her dead in her bed.
その母親だがね
ベッドの上で亡くなっていたそうなんだよ
She had clearly been murdered.
状況的には明らかに他殺
The stress of caring for her...
介護の疲れ 三組の災厄
The Class 3 calamity...
Perhaps he felt so trapped by it all
のっぴきならない精神状態に追い込まれて
母親を危めてしまった
that it drove him to kill his own mother.
ということなんだろうな
そして自らの教え子の前で自殺した
And then he killed himself
in front of his students.
Why would he make such extreme decisions?
どう思う この常軌を逸した選択を
You think this was a result
of the phenomenon?
これも「現象」の結果だと
Yes.
So he was drawn into death
by otherwise unlikely means?
だから 普通なら起こりえない形で
死に引き込まれてしまった
そう考えるのが妥当だろ
Could there be any other explanation?
The calamity hasn't been stopped.
災厄は止まらない
これからも 人が死ぬ
People will keep dying.
There was nothing we could do.
仕方ねえよ
な サカキ そう落ち込むなって
Come on, Sakaki, don't get so down.
Do Not Enter
自分を責めたってよ
Blaming yourself won't change anything.
今更どうにもなんねえよ
ついこの間までさあ
Until recently, you were...
Yeah, and it was breaking my heart!
そりゃあ心が痛んださあ
You know the whole story now, right?
事情はもう全部知ってんだろう
だったら 察してくれよな
So you get where I'm coming from?
Yes, I understand perfectly well.
十分に察してるよ
分かってる
What about you, Misaki?
Feel like a weight's been lifted?
見崎も肩の荷が下りたって感じか
Hard to say.
さあ もともと重くなんてなかったし
I didn't really feel a weight to begin with.
You are seriously weird.
やっぱお前変わってんな
Here you are.
ここか
何だよ お前いきなり
Jeez, what's your problem?
You both might exist again,
「いないもの」は終わったけど
but you'd best be prepared.
一応は覚悟しておいてね
For what?
何
It's your fault.
「あなたたちのせいよ」
H... Hey!
お おい
People will say that.
There's no way you'll be considered
completely innocent,
お互いまったく責任が無いとはいえないし
and I'm sure I'll be accused
of incompetence, as well.
私も「無能」の謗りを受けても仕方なし
True.
そうだね
Where do you stand?
お前はどうなんだよ
I can't blame Kouichi,
恒一くんのせいにはできない
no matter what anyone says.
いくらなんでもね
But it's not over.
まだ終わってない
災厄も 対策係の仕事も
The calamity, and my work as
head of countermeasures,
are only just beginning.
まだまだこれからよ
I wonder if anyone will go into hiding now,
until summer break?
このまま夏休みまで出て来ない人もいるのかな
Definitely.
絶対いるね
Some people may have fled town already.
もう町から脱出した人いるかも
You think?
脱出
Yes, it happens every year.
そう 毎年いるらしいから
There are always people who leave
Yomiyama for summer break.
夏休みに夜見山から逃げ出す人たち
うん なんだかな
It's all so strange.
But you really are weird, Misaki.
にしても見崎 やっぱお前って変わってんな
You talk like this doesn't involve you.
人事みたいに淡々とさ
そう
Do I?
Could it be that you're
actually the extra this year?
実はお前が本当に今年の「もう一人」だったりして
It could very well be you, you know.
当の勅使河原くんがそうかもしれないよ
M... Me? No way!
お 俺
まさか
Don't even joke about that.
冗談はなしね
There's really no way?
本当にまさか
No, no, no!
いやいやいや 死んだなんて心当たりはこれっぽっちもねえし
I have no memories of dying!
And, not to brag,
自慢じゃないが
but I clearly remember all the
shit I got into as a kid!
がきの頃やらかしたことは はっきり覚えてるし
You look well.
元気そうだね
Thanks.
おかげさまで
Was Akazawa here to talk to
you about something?
赤沢さん 千曳さんになにか
As head of countermeasures,
she comes here often.
対策係だからね
ここにはよく来る
I see.
そうだったんだ
She's a strong girl, and she knows that,
彼女は強い子だし
本人もそれに自覚的なんだが
but considering what she's up against...
戦いを挑む相手がな
I pity her.
不憫でならんよ
By the way, Ms. Mikami dropped by today too.
ああ そういえば 今日は三神先生も来られてね
Ms. Mikami?
三神 先生が
She knows my history here.
私の経歴については彼女も知ってるからね
それで改まって相談をと
There was something she
wanted to formally discuss.
And what brings you two here?
で 君たちは
I wanted to ask about fifteen years ago,
when the calamity stopped midyear.
十五年前 途中で止まったという話を聞いたんです
それで
That was the one time
in the past twenty-five years
この二十五年間で唯一途中で止まった年だ
when it stopped midyear.
April 12, sister, Kyouko, illness
July 23, sister, Ikumi, illness
June 6, accident
Excluding Ritsuko, whom I didn't know about,
there were seven deaths that year.
その年度の犠牲者は
私が把握できていなかった理津子くんを除けば七人
June 6, accident
June 13, accident
August 9, accident
理津子くんはいつ
When did Ritsuko die?
In July.
七月です
June 13, accident
August 9, accident
Wait...
これは
Does that mean the deaths
stopped in August?
八月で止まったということですか
Yes, and look at the date
of the August deaths.
そ 八月の日付けを見てご覧
August 9...
八月九日
That class had just left
for a class trip on August 8.
実は その年の三組は八月八日から合宿を行っててね
Class trip?
合宿
I think something may have
happened during summer break...
確か夏休み何かが
So, two students died in
accidents on that trip?
その合宿で二人が事故に
そして その合宿で何かがあって
And something happened on that trip
that stopped the calamity?
災厄が止まった
So it would seem.
おそらく そのページ 「死者」の名前が書かれてないだろう
August 9, accident
Notice that no one is listed as
"deceased" on that page.
Deceased:
It never became clear who
the dead person was that year.
誰が「死者」だったのか その年は確認できなかったんだよ
Why did it stop?
何故 止まったんですか
I'm not certain.
はっきりとは分からない
But I do know that they visited
the Yomiyama Shrine.
ただ合宿中に夜見山神社へお参りに行ったらしい
A shrine?
神社
A very old shrine,
located halfway up Mt. Yomiyama.
古い神社だ
「夜見山」という山の中腹にある
Their lodge was at
the foot of that mountain.
合宿施設もその山のふもとでよ
So, maybe if we visit the shrine...
じゃ その神社へお参りに行けば
Naturally, people went back to it in years
when the calamity occurred,
当然 その後の「ある年」にお参りに行ったようだが
but it had no effect.
効果は しかし なかった
So the shrine had nothing to do with it?
意味は無かった
No, that's not conclusive.
いえ 断定はできない
It could be that going there in a large group,
in early August, was effective.
八月上旬に大勢で行ったから効果があったの かもしれない
Of course, we can't deny the
possibility that the effect came
お参りとは関係なく
別に何かがあった
from something else,
unrelated to visiting the shrine.
という可能性も無論否定できない
This is what Ms. Mikami came here
to discuss with me today.
実は今日 三神先生が来られた時もこの話になってね
July 17 (Fri)
This may seem abrupt,
急な話ですが
but from August 8th to the 10th,
八月八日から十日まで二泊三日のクラス合宿を行います
we will be conducting a class trip
for three days and two nights.
Please prioritize this event,
これは大切な行事だと思ってください
and plan to participate, if at all possible.
都合のつく人はできるだけ参加してください
You will receive additional details
in the coming days.
詳細については近日中に皆さんにプリントをお送りします
I will mail the forms to all of you.
Question!
質問
Ms. Mikami?
先生
Who is dead?
「死者」は誰
「死者」は 誰
The dead one...
「死者」は あなた
...is you.
ぼ 僕
M... Me?
Dad
Hello?
はい
I swear, India just gets hotter and hotter!
Hello?
まーすます暑いぞ インドは
I swear, India just gets hotter and hotter!
How've you been, kiddo?
元気でやってるか
Fine, I guess.
まあまあだね
Yeah.
Yeah, everyone's doing well.
皆元気にしてるよ
Hey, Dad?
あのさ お父さん
Have you ever seen any of Mom's
photos from junior high?
お母さんの中学時代の写真って見たことある
Photos?
写真
卒業アルバムは確か 婚約した頃に見せてくれたな
I'm pretty sure she showed me her
graduation album when we got engaged.
Any others?
他の写真は
Like, have you seen the
group photo her class took
中学の卒業式の日に撮ったっていう集合写真って 見たことある
after their graduation ceremony?
集合写真 何でまた
Group photo? Why do you ask?
Well, I've heard that it was kind of weird.
その ちょっと変な写真だったって
Do Not Enter
Like, a ghost photo.
えっと 心霊写真みたいな
どこで仕入れて来たんだ そんなような話
Where did you hear a silly story like that?
For one thing, ghost photos are just...
だいたいお前 心霊写真なんてものはだな
Well, it's just...
いや あの
Oh, now that you mention it,
I might have heard a story like that,
a long time ago.
そういえば昔 そんな話を聞いたっけなあ
Something about a creepy photo.
Did you see it?
気味の悪い写真があるんだって
Nope.
見たの その写真
いや 身近にあるのは嫌だから 実家においてきたとか
She didn't like having it near her,
so she left it at her parents' place.
Her parents' place?
実家に
Hey, Kouichi, something goin' on there?
おい 恒一 そっちで何かあったのか
No, nothing.
あっ ないない ちょっと退屈なだけ
I'm just kinda bored.
Ah...
そうか
You know, Ritsuko was a very special lady.
理津子はな 本当に魅力的な人だったぞ
My feelings for her haven't changed a bit.
私のあいつに対する気持ちは今でもまったく変わってない
And that's why you're my...
だから 恒一 お前は私にとって
Okay, I get it!
分かった 分かった
Later!
じゃあ またね
Inoya?
イノヤ
そのお店の場所は知ってるけどさあ
Yeah, I know where that is, but...
Today?
今日
Come on, dude!
何だよ
Don't tell me...
もしかして 鳴ちゃんとデートか
You got a date with Mei?
Well? What is it you want to talk about?
で 何の話
It's gotta be in person.
とにかく 直に会って話したいんだよ
If you've got a date, just bring Mei along.
デートなら 彼女も連れて来いよ
This problem involves
the whole class, after all.
クラスの問題でもあるしな
All right, I'll be there.
じゃあ 行くよ
Kouichi!
恒一くん こっちよ
Over here.
Akazawa?
赤沢さん
Teshigawara called you here, right?
勅使河原に呼ばれてきたんでしょう
Um...
えっと
Have a seat.
座ったら
He called you, too?
赤沢さんも
Yes.
そっ クラスの問題だっていうから
Only because he said it
"involves the whole class."
I wouldn't go anywhere
at his invitation otherwise.
じゃなきゃ あんな男に呼び出されて 出て来るわけない
Teshigawara filled me in on
what happened fifteen years ago.
勅使河原から大体聞いた
十五年前の話
その 恒一くんのお母さんのことも
And about your mom, too.
Oh...
そう
Welcome.
いらっしゃい
A friend of yours, Izumi?
泉美ちゃんのお友達
Yes.
ええ クラスメートの榊原恒一くんです
This is my classmate, Kouichi Sakakibara.
Oh, that must make you Yuuya's friend, too.
あら じゃあ 優矢くんのお友達ね
Thanks for being so kind to my brother.
いつも弟がお世話になってます
I'm Yuuya Mochizuki's older sister, Tomoka.
望月優矢の姉の智香です 初めまして
Nice to meet you.
Oh, yes, likewise.
ああ はい 初めまして
Yuuya has told me a lot about you.
色々聞いてますよ 優矢くんからは
What can I get for you?
ご注文は
Oh, let me see...
えっ えっと
He'll have the same as me.
私と同じやつを
Oh...
あら 畏まりました
Coming right up.
What did you get?
赤沢さん 何飲んでるの
Coffee.
コーヒー
I don't like coffee; it's too bitter.
僕 コーヒー苦くて飲めないんだけど
Well, the coffee here is the real deal.
ここのコーヒーは本物よ
They use Hawaiian Kona Extra Fancy beans.
ハワイコナのエクストラファンシー
Thank you for waiting.
お待たせしました ごゆっくりどうぞ
Please enjoy.
Just take my word for it.
騙されたと思って　そのまま飲んでみて
Give it a try.
It's bitter, but also sweet.
苦いけど 甘い
I like it.
美味しいね これ
So, you didn't go back to Tokyo?
恒一くん 東京帰らなかったんだ
No, it would feel like I was
running away, and...
うん 逃げ出すみたいで ちょっとね
I've started to wonder if it's me who's dead.
僕が「死者」じゃないかって 疑ってる
Maybe you were never born.
あなた 生まれていないのかもしれない
Maybe fifteen years ago,
十五年前 「災厄」であなたのお母様が亡くなられた
the calamity took your mother's life,
and she couldn't give birth to you.
そして あなたも 生まれてこられなかった
And now, fifteen years later,
それから 十五年経った今
you've come back to life as a
transfer student in Class 3.
あなたが転校生として 三組に復活した
That's...
バカな
That's ridiculous.
そんなバカな話
Don't take me so seriously.
本気にしないでね
True, I did consider the possibility,
その可能性を考えたのは本当
but...
でもね
Shake my hand.
握手
やっぱり あなたとどこかで会った
I still get the feeling that we've met...
No, that I've shaken
your hand somewhere before.
ううん どこかで握手したことがあると思う
You think so?
えっ そうかな
I can't call up a visual memory,
頭の記憶としては残っていないけど
but my hand physically remembers yours.
手がね 体が覚えてる
Now that you mention it,
そういえば 病院でも握手したよね
you shook my hand at the hospital, too.
Did you do that for a reason?
あれって意味があるの
There's a rumor that dead people
have shockingly cold hands.
死者の手は驚くほど冷たいって 噂がね
I doubt it's true, though.
でも たぶん嘘ね
If it were that easy to tell...
そんな簡単な方法で分かるんなら
Welcome.
あら いらっしゃい
Sorry I'm late.
ごめん ごめん
Hey, guys!
お待たせ
What'd you do that for?
何それ
Do you hate me that much?
俺 そんなに嫌われてる
Want the truth?
はっきり言われたい
I wouldn't mind...
それも悪くねえが
まあ 今日はいいや
Oh, whatever, I'll let it slide today.
What did you want to talk about?
話って何
You tell them, Mochizuki.
望月 お前が話すよな
Okay.
Since there's a chance
今回の件 お姉さんも巻き込まれちゃう可能性だってあるから
that my sister could become involved
in what's going on...
Oh, my sister is...
あの 僕のお姉さんって
Tomoka, right?
智香さんだよね
Yeah.
うん それでね 僕 どうしても黙っていられなくて
Anyway, I just couldn't keep quiet about it.
You told her?
事情を話した
Down to the details.
かなり詳しく
She went to Yomi North, too,
お姉さんもやっぱり 夜見北の出身で
so she knew the rumors about Class 3.
三組の噂は知ってたみたい
And Tomoka actually gave us
a surprising bit of info.
そこでだ
その智香さんから びっくり情報が出てきたんだな
One of our regulars is
a man named Katsumi Matsunaga.
松永克巳って人で うちの常連さんなんだけど
I knew he went to Yomi North,
夜見北の出身だとは知っていたんだけど
but I recently found out that
he was in Class 3.
三年三組だったって知ったのは 最近のことでね
I worked up the courage to ask him
それで 思い切って訪ねてみたの
if it had happened in his year.
「松永さんの年は「ある年」だったのか」って
And he said...
そうしたらね
The curse that year wasn't...
あの年の呪いは俺が 俺は悪くないんだ
It wasn't my fault.
I saved them all.
皆を助けたんだ
I saved them!
助けたんだよ 俺が
I knew I had to tell them, so that's why...
だから 伝えなきゃと思って
残したんだ 「あれ」を
I left it there.
What does that mean?
どういう意味なんですか 「あれ」って
Left what, where?
He couldn't seem to recall.
あの人まるで覚えてなくて
I've asked him about it many times,
but he insists he has no idea.
あの後 いくら聞いても 「知らない」っていうばかりで
Makes you curious, doesn't it?
気になるだろう この話
This Matsunaga guy stopped the calamity?
松永という人が 「災厄」を止めた
And he left a hint on how
he did it somewhere?
そして その手がかりをどこかに残した
That's gotta be it.
ってことだよな
So, I'm thinking we should talk to
this Matsunaga guy ourselves.
でだ その松永ってやつに 俺たちも話を聞いてみようかと思うんだが
Do you know where we can find him?
その松永って人はどこに
No, I don't know where he lives.
どこに住んでいるかまでは
Then...
それじゃあ
Don't you know someone who
was in Matsunaga's class?
恒一くん あなたの身近に松永さんの同級生がいなかった
Oh, so he was your aunt's classmate.
そう おばさんの同級生なんだ
If I find out where Matsunaga is,
もし 松永って人の居場所が分かったら
will you come with me to see him?
見崎も一緒に行く
You really were the model for
that doll, weren't you?
その人形 やっぱり君がモデルなんだよね
You said only half,
but it looks just like you.
半分だけって言ってたけど
そっくりだし
This girl is the daughter she
gave birth to twelve years ago.
この子はね 十二年前にあの人が産んだ子
Your sister?
えっ 妹さん
But she was stillborn.
だけど 生まれた時には死んじゃってた子
She made this doll
これはね あの人が生きられなかった我が子を思いながら作った人形
based on the daughter
who never had a chance to live.
So, it's only half me, if not less.
だから 私は半分か それ以下
Actually, I have somewhere to be tomorrow.
実はね 私明日から出かけなきゃならないの
Oh? Where?
えっ どこへ
My parents want me to go with
them to their summer house.
お父さんとお母さん 私と 三人で別荘へ行こうって
I couldn't tell them I don't want to.
いやだっていうわけにもいかなくて
Is it outside Yomiyama?
夜見山市の外
Yes.
そう
So you're leaving town?
町から脱出
We'll only be gone a week.
一週間ほどで帰る予定だから
I'll be back for the class trip.
戻ってきて 合宿にも行くつもり
Oh...
そっか
Hey, have you found that ghost picture your
mother left at her parents' house?
ね 実家にあるかもって言ってた例の集合写真 見つかった
No, not yet.
いや まだ
If you find it, will you show me?
見つかったら その写真 見せてくれる
Sure.
If anything comes up, use this number.
何かあったら この番号に
これって 電話番号
Is this a phone number?
For a cell phone?
携帯の
Yes.
そうよ
Yours?
見崎の
Yes.
そう
You said you hated those devices.
いやな機械なんて言ってたくせに
I do.
本当にいやなの
Being connected to people all the time by
electromagnetic waves disturbs me.
四六時中電波で繋がってるなんて 気持ち悪い
Then why do you have one?
なのに どうして
She makes me carry it.
持たされてるの
She claims to feel uneasy at times.
偶にあの人 不安で仕方なくなるみたいで
I see.
そうなんだ
By the way...
そういえば
Yes?
えっ なに
You said you wondered if it's you who's dead.
自分が「死者」なんじゃないか疑ってみたって言ってたけど
Yeah...
Has your suspicion been laid to rest?
疑いは解けた
Yeah...
Huh?
あれ
New dolls are put in here.
新しい人形がこの中に納められるみたい
Don't worry.
安心して
It's not you.
「死者」じゃない
You're not the one who's dead.
榊原くんは 「死者」じゃないから
Like film that loses its color with time
色褪せてく フィルムのように
The now that we know will one day fade
確かな今も いずれ霞んで
That fleeting moment's light
何でもなく 笑いあった
When we shared a laugh over nothing
刹那の時間と光
It now lies, waiting to be found, at the depths
繋がってゆく 記憶の底に
Of memories that connect one to the next
誰かが見つけるためあると信じてる 今でも
This I still believe
"Hair stand"